<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Note on Homepage of Vašek</title>
    <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/tags/note/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Note on Homepage of Vašek</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>© Václav Blažej</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vaclavblazej.github.io/tags/note/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Over the Garden Wall</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/over_the_garden_wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/over_the_garden_wall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I heard about &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/video/vi3766598681/?playlistId=tt3718778&amp;amp;ref_=tt_ov_vi&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Over The Garden Wall&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; series for the first time two days ago.&#xA;It is an almost 10 years old miniseries with runtime of 1 hour 40 minutes.&#xA;It is rare to find a series with so much care given to it; I can wholeheartedly recommend it.&#xA;The miniseries format gives it a short runtime and gave the creators incentive to tie all the knots, an important feature that I seek in any series that I consider watching.&#xA;I will not do a thorough analysis of the series as it seems internet has enough of those.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/evolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evolution&lt;/em&gt; is a process where an object adjust to the environment through change over time.&#xA;For an evolution to appear we need two factors.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Objects that can multiply and change&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Environment that enforces the change&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Both are necessary and sufficient.&#xA;Without objects we have no things to evolve.&#xA;If they could not multiply than we only have self-improvement.&#xA;Without environmental pressure the changes do not lead anywhere.&#xA;Note that the improvement is always with respect to the environment &amp;ndash; there is no evolution for its own sake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on AI</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Phrase &lt;em&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/em&gt; is changing its meaning quickly.&#xA;In about 2012, I would say it is a sci-fi concept or a game&amp;rsquo;s opponent controlled by a computer.&#xA;In 2017 this was very similar, but AI seemed to encompass gradient descent and fancy heuristics.&#xA;Everyone was creating &amp;ldquo;chat-bots&amp;rdquo; that I never found anywhere close to useful, even for their dedicated purpose.&#xA;(E.g. our school had big PR news about our awesome chatbot about Covid 2019; it didn&amp;rsquo;t have reasonable answers even for the most basic questions.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About rants</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/rant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/rant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to be consistent about anything.&#xA;In good mood I decide to do something, then priorities change and I stop it.&#xA;But the big ideas always boomerang back to me and I find myself thinking about them again.&#xA;I am very glad that five years ago circumstances made me create this website.&#xA;To an accidental reader, I wish to convey that it serves as a overview of my past thoughts.&#xA;So I find it unlikely that any content will be retroactively changed aside from grammar and spell corrections, or for structural rearrangement (moving files elsewhere).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dredge</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/dredge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/dredge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1562430/DREDGE/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Dredge&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a single-player fisihing adventure with a sinister undercurrent&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; as Steam says.&#xA;I do not want to spoil anything so I split this post into several sections with gradually increasing amount of spoilers.&#xA;Let me start with a spoiler-free review.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Dredge is awesome.&#xA;You end up on an island, you have a ship, go fishing - which is implemented via a simple mini-game, sell your catch, talk to townsfolk, discover the islands.&#xA;Along with the fishing minigame there is a space-management mini-game.&#xA;Some notable features that you discover very early (or on the steam page) are:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initialization of Parameters hierarchy website</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/parameters/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/parameters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the last two weeks I set up &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vaclavblazej/parameters&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;repository&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which generates &lt;a href=&#34;https://vaclavblazej.github.io/parameters/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;website&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; about parameterized complexity.&#xA;More specifically, it depicts hierarchy of various parameters.&#xA;This project was on my mind for a while and wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how to do it, but then realized it will be quite easy to do with a static website.&#xA;I use static web generator for my homepage and understand it well enough to setup any other site.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patrick&#39;s Parabox</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/patricks_parabox/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/patricks_parabox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I finished &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1260520/Patricks_Parabox/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Parabox&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and can recommend it to anyone who likes puzzle games.&#xA;The whole game is in-theme and the production is very good.&#xA;Great deal of planning seems to have gone into the puzzles and their progression is well thought-out.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;patrick.png&#34; alt=&#34;patrick&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The game uses well-known and easy-to-understand Sokoban mechanics while always adding something new to them.&#xA;The main change is that each block that player usually pushes is itself a map and can under some circumstances be entered and exited.&#xA;Though the game is 2D it reminded me of Portal because it introduces and explores this map-mechanic in-depth and its interaction with many other cute mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intense work</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/work/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the last fourteen days, I&amp;rsquo;ve been engrossed in my work.&#xA;The process is enjoyable but each day flies by fairly quickly.&#xA;On the other hand, looking back at this time so much was done that it feels like a long interval even though it is not.&#xA;I guess you do not have time to notice the time goes by when things are happening.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During work, I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying the new Gorillaz album.&#xA;It is surreal to see this group make a new album even though I have fond memories of listening to their &amp;lsquo;&amp;rsquo;then-current&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; songs as a child.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automation</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/automatization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/automatization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A big part of programmer&amp;rsquo;s job is to automate processes.&#xA;Some people find this activity very satisfying and enjoy programming because of it.&#xA;The same feeling, but arguably stronger, can be achieved in games such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.factorio.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Factorio&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1812820/Bitburner/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bitburner&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The goal of automating something is to make a repetitive task easier or (ideally) entirely automatic.&#xA;We shall consider only tasks that can be done on a computer.&#xA;We categorize tasks into several levels of abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Let old posts decompose</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/old_posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/old_posts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are two types of information you can find on the internet.&#xA;The first presents new information that decays with time.&#xA;The second is more persistent.&#xA;I wish to elaborate on cases where the second type turns into the first type unintentionally.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;On the creation of this website, I had an unachievable dream of presenting a database of algorithms together with experiments that would compare various approaches or implementations.&#xA;This attempt is hinted at in one of the first posts: &lt;a href=&#34;https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2015/polymul&#34;&gt;Polynomial multiplication&lt;/a&gt; (in Czech) which compares three different multiplication methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posts in 2023?</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/posts/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2023/posts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi!&#xA;So, I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking whether to write more posts on this blog and decided to create a post every week.&#xA;Then three weeks went by and I did not finish any single post.&#xA;So let me try again.&#xA;I claim that I&amp;rsquo;ll do a post each week from now on &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;ll see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My main motivation is to improve in non-technical (but also technical) writing.&#xA;I spend majority of my time slowly writing a precise text or going over it again and again, making sure it is correct, or writing code (which is basically the same thing).&#xA;This blog shall serve the other side of the writing profession &amp;ndash; writing more spontaneously and learning how to spell words (no, it&amp;rsquo;s not spotaneougly).&#xA;No one improved their writing style by not writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MBTI</title>
      <link>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2021/mbti/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vaclavblazej.github.io/post/2021/mbti/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Myers–Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI) is a way to classify psychological preferences in how people perceive the world and make decisions, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myers%E2%80%93Briggs_Type_Indicator&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for more descriptions.&#xA;The test which sets you in a specific box can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.16personalities.com/&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;online&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, however I view these tests as an interesting entry point to the theory, but ultimately, they say how a person behaves, not how person thinks.&#xA;To make self-classification, one can simply use a pretty nice &lt;a href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/1/1f/MyersBriggsTypes.png/1024px-MyersBriggsTypes.png&#34;target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;chart&lt;span style=&#34;white-space: nowrap;&#34;&gt;&amp;thinsp;↗&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is present on wikipedia as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
