<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on Homepage of Vašek</title>
    <link>https://blazeva1.pages.fit/tags/philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on Homepage of Vašek</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>blazeva1 -a- fit.cvut.cz &lt;Václav Blažej&gt; (Václav Blažej)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>blazeva1 -a- fit.cvut.cz &lt;Václav Blažej&gt; (Václav Blažej)</webMaster>
    <copyright>© Václav Blažej</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://blazeva1.pages.fit/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thought experiment on continuous consciousness within many worlds universe interpretation</title>
      <link>https://blazeva1.pages.fit/post/2023/manyworlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>blazeva1 -a- fit.cvut.cz &lt;Václav Blažej&gt; (Václav Blažej)</author>
      <guid>https://blazeva1.pages.fit/post/2023/manyworlds/</guid>
      <description>In TV mini series Devs&amp;thinsp;↗ a claim within the many world hypothesis is posed: If one&amp;rsquo;s survival depends on a quantum fluctuation, then their consciousness lives on in the world where it did not end. In my opinion, this leads to one of the more thought provoking scenes of the show.&#xA;Content warning: The following thoughts discuss death and suicide and will be disturbing to some readers. Carefully consider whether reading further is worth the risk.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On life, consciousness, and soul</title>
      <link>https://blazeva1.pages.fit/post/2022/consciousness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>blazeva1 -a- fit.cvut.cz &lt;Václav Blažej&gt; (Václav Blažej)</author>
      <guid>https://blazeva1.pages.fit/post/2022/consciousness/</guid>
      <description>Where do you go when you sleep? Where do you go when you die? To clear these thoughts in my mind I decided to write a little post.&#xA;Each individual has freedom in what to believe in and from a selfish point of view, it makes sense to believe in what makes the individual more comfortable. Believe in soul and face philosophical questions of &amp;ldquo;what is soul and consciousness.&amp;rdquo; The purely materialistic view of the world has reasonable answers for those but, as mentioned, it may be beneficial to ignore them.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
